In this series of videos, we're going to discuss some of the environments of ZOS UNIX,
such as the language environment, debugging, and callable services.
We're going to split the discussion between application programming in ZOS UNIX,
so we're talking here about things like compiling, running, porting, and debugging applications,
and some additional considerations like access control lists and data sharing.
So let's get started.
Shown here is an example of a C program which reads data from a hierarchical file
and displays the results on the screen.
The ZOS UNIX C89 CC C++ utility is used to compile and link edit ZOS UNIX C and ZOS applications.
Programs can be compiled and linked edited in one step,
or the link edit of the object modules can be performed in a separate step from the compilation.
In order for the C89 CC and C++ to perform C and C++ compiles,
the ZOS C and C++ optional feature must be installed on the system.
ZOS UNIX supports different environments where ZOS UNIX C and MVS applications can run.
A ZOS UNIX shell program can be run by specifying the program name on the command line,
or the program can be called from a shell script.
Also, a program residing in a ZOS dataset can be run from the shell
by using a tsoe call command to pass a call to the program through tsoe.
Applications can also run in a ZOS UNIX shell in the ZOS batch by using the bpx bags program,
or a ZOS UNIX program which resides in a ZOS dataset can be run from tsoe.
A ZOS UNIX program which resides in a ZOS dataset can be run in batch
using the JCL exec statement to start the program.
The appropriate locale for an application can be set by using the set locale function.
For example, an application can define set locale LC underscore all comma C,
meaning all the categories of variables must comply to the default C language definition,
or another example is set locale LC underscore monetary comma UK,
which would use the UK English monetary definition of pound sterling.
Enhanced ASCII support with file tagging and auto conversion makes it easier to port
UNIX programs from the original ASCII environment to the ZOS environment,
which is an EBSIDIC environment. Before this support, if the original program
was written with ASCII dependent data handling in C or C++,
it might not be ported directly to ZOS without changes in the program.
The CCSID of a program is set at compile time.
The CCSID tag of file can be set by the ch tag shell command.
With auto conversion, an EBSIDIC program does not need to know
that it is reading and writing to an ASCII file.
Conversion is done if it needs to be.
ZOS system components need fast any mode code page conversion and other services.
The solution is Unicode conversion services, along with IBM Z hardware assists.
ZOS can provide support for the conversion of Unicode data,
either UTF-8 or UTF-16, to any of the EBSIDIC CCSIDs currently supported by your applications.
If you intend to make use of this capability, you must enable the ZOS conversion services
and install a conversion image which specifies the conversion that you want your application to perform.
IBM Ported Tools for ZOS is a non-priced program product
designed to deliver tools and applications for the ZOS platform.
These applications have been modified to operate within the ZOS environment.
Ported Tools for ZOS includes the Perl scripting language as well as the OpenSSH secure shell.
After your C or C++ program has been developed,
you can take advantage of the ZOS Unix Debugger with its DBX utility
to debug the program from within the shell environment on a ZOS system.
DBX is a process-oriented debugger. It runs in a different process or address space than
the process being debugged. It provides multi-process debug across fork exec and
has the capability to attach to and debug a process that is already executing.
DBX debugged signals that are sent to the process being debugged.
It also debugs at machine level using machine registers and examines memory addresses.
High level languages or HLLs which support calls to assembler subroutines
can use the ZOS Unix callable services.
The application programmer is responsible for ensuring that the correct environment exists.
One reason to use the callable services from HLLs is to get access to data in the
hierarchical file system. The concept of sockets provides the application programmer
with an interface which is very similar to that used for file IO in the C language.
The IO operations used for file access and network access have the same names but the
functions performed are different. User-written socket applications can use TCPIP services as a
communication vehicle. Both client and server socket applications can use the socket interface
to communicate over the internet and between other socket applications by using local sockets.
An assembler interface is also provided for those applications that do not use the C or C++
runtime library. ZOS Unix supports two types of socket families. Unix domain sockets,
also called local sockets, are part of the Unix address family AF underscore Unix.
AF underscore Unix sockets provide communication between processes on a single system and internet
protocol sockets are part of the internet address family AF underscore INET for IPv4 and AF underscore
INET6 for IPv6. In the next video we'll look at printing and ACLs.